<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Væ-Euge-Tuba. Or, The vvo-joy-trumpet, sounding the third and greatest woe to the Antichristian world, but the first and last joy to the church of the saints upon Christs exaltation over the kingdomes of the world. Unfolded in a sermon before the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament, at their late solemne fast, May 26. 1647. / By G. Hughes Minister of the Gospell in Plymouth. Published by order of the House.</title>
            <author>Hughes, George, 1603-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E389_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201523</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862023</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E389[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Væ-Euge-Tuba. Or, The vvo-joy-trumpet, sounding the third and greatest woe to the Antichristian world, but the first and last joy to the church of the saints upon Christs exaltation over the kingdomes of the world. Unfolded in a sermon before the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament, at their late solemne fast, May 26. 1647. / By G. Hughes Minister of the Gospell in Plymouth. Published by order of the House.</title>
                  <author>Hughes, George, 1603-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.G. for Iohn Rothwell at the Sunne and Fountaine in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647:.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelations XI, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114171:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VAE-EUGE-TUBA. <hi>OR,</hi> The Wo-Ioy-Trumpet, Sounding the third and greateſt woe to the Antichriſtian world, but the firſt and laſt joy to the Church of the Saints upon Chriſts exaltation over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the World.</p>
            <p>UNFOLDED IN A SERMON before the Honourable Houſes of COMMONS aſſembled in Parliament, at their late ſolemne Faſt, <hi>May</hi> 26. 1647.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> G. HUGHES <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpell in Plymouth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order of the Houſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 8.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>By me Kings reigne, and Princes decree juſtice.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>OBAD. V. 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Kingdome ſhall be the Lords.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Rothwell</hi> at the Sunne and Fountaine in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1647:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:114171:2"/>
            <head>Die Mercurii, Maii <hi>26. 1647.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ORdered that Sir <hi>John Bampfyld</hi> doe from this Houſe give thanks to Maſter <hi>Hughes</hi> for the great paines he tooke in the Sermon he preached this day at the intreaty of this Houſe at St. <hi>Margarets</hi> Weſtminſter (it being the day of publique Humiliation) and to deſire him to print his Sermon: and he is to have the like priviledge in printing of it as others in the like kind uſually have had.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>I doe appoint <hi>John Rothwell</hi> to print my Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Hughes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114171:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE THE Houſe of COMMONS now Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable and Renowned Patriots,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a pretty Rhetoricall ſtraine of words, though ſcarce reaſonable (unleſſe as a Paradox may be made) with Moraliſts or Divines,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Longin <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>To fall in great matters is a Generous and Noble ſinne.</hi> It is but a conceit, that the height of materials where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about
<pb facs="tcp:114171:3"/>the ſlip was, ſhould innoble ſinne; Falſe coinage upon Lead will be as high Treaſon as that upon better mettall; and Treaſon upon Gold as baſe as that upon Braſſe.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Oracles</hi> of God, where we have words not inferiour to mens, but wiſdome and truth farre above them, We are thus taught, <hi>Slips in higheſt things are the greateſt faults,</hi> and <hi>a fall in Heaven fouler wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe than a ſtumbling on earth.</hi> Sinnes draw the higheſt aggravations from the Greatneſſe of God againſt whom, and the height of place wherein they are committed. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels which left their firſt ſtation, and man that ſinned in Paradiſe, have felt the truth of this. Zeale for God and you, and his Church, (moſt Noble Worthies) wil make his &amp; your friends reckon little of their lives to keep you that are in Higheſt places from ſuch high tranſgreſſion. By the grace given to me, when I was called by you to ſpeak from God to you, &amp; for you to God, in the day of your ſoules affliction, I had this in my greateſt deſires, to keepe you that are in higheſt places, and mannaging the higheſt matters of God, from ſinne againſt him. I
<pb facs="tcp:114171:3"/>therefore (as became a Miniſter of Chriſt) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to uſe all plainneſſe in ſetting out the <hi>Kingdome of our Lord,</hi> unto which all <hi>States</hi> muſt how that would be proſperous, and in pointing at ſuch ſinfull irregularities which render God an enemy irreconcileable, and ſuch States thereby eternally miſerable. In all which (the Judge of ſpirits knows) I intended not either by matter or form of ſpeech to be ſpatter <hi>ſuch an Honourable Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> with falſe charges, or make a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> vile among the people; (I have learned better of Chriſt by Gods grace) my aime was onely to be a faithfull Remembrancer of you from God, of the fatall diſeaſes whereunto ſuch <hi>Politique Bodies</hi> may be ſubject, in their members; that a timely care may be had of purging your ſelves, leaſt death enſue.</p>
            <p>I hope your hearts are as willing to beare ſuch plainneſſe, as God would have them in commanding it. Never was there a more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall character upon the <hi>State of Iſrael,</hi> then that bitter ſpeech of <hi>Idolatrous Amaziah</hi> to <hi>Ieroboam</hi> againſt <hi>honeſt Amos, The Land is not able to bear his words.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 7.10.</note> When States
<pb facs="tcp:114171:4"/>cannot <hi>beare</hi> ſound words from God, ſpoken in his Name; or not <hi>ſo beare</hi> them, as obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to anſwer Gods mind in them, the doom of <hi>Elies ſonnes</hi> will cleave to them.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.25.</note> The God of all grace keepe off ſuch a curſe of an <hi>Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient hardned ſpirit</hi> from you, and give you the bleſſing of a <hi>boared eare, and a ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeelding-obedient heart,</hi> ſo ſhall ye proſper.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon your Order of <hi>acceptance</hi> of theſe poore labours, and for publiſhing the ſame, I have been obedient to your deſire; and now in all humble duty and thankefulneſſe doe preſent that to your eyes, of which your eares have taſted; I have made a few additions for clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſome paſſages which ſtraits of time then ſhut out; I hope none will be looſers by them. The height of my ambition is,<note place="margin">2 Cor 3.3.</note> that by this <hi>Inke-worke</hi> the <hi>Spirit of the living God</hi> would write the <hi>Name of the Lord and his Chriſt</hi> upon this Parliament, and upon the people of the Land; that ye may be the <hi>Lords State,</hi> ruling for Chriſt, and he in you, as one Party; and they the <hi>Lords</hi> people, the lot of his Inheritance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114171:4"/>
            <p>And now having done my worke with you, I ſhall by the good will of our God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to my place, and there labour for you, to helpe on the work of Righteouſneſſe, Truth, and Peace, in your hands. My ſuit to the Thron of grace is and ſhall be the <hi>Averſion</hi> of all thoſe <hi>Woes</hi> ſounded by this Trumpet upon the wicked, and the <hi>Accompliſhment</hi> of all thoſe <hi>Woes</hi> ſounded to the Church; that Chriſt may be fully exalted in theſe united Kingdoms and reign, that the Churches of the Saints alſo may ſing, and alwaies rejoyce in their Lord, whoſe theſe Kingdomes are; and all in your daies, and by your power mannaged graciouſly in the band of <hi>our Lord.</hi> By whoſe command I muſt ſigne my ſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble and faithfull ſervant in the Kingdom of Chriſt, GEORGE HUGHES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:114171:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114171:5"/>
            <head>THE WOE-JOY TRUMPET.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Revel. c. 11. v. 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the ſeventh Angel ſounded the Trumpet, and there were great voices in Heaven, ſaying, The Kingdomes of this world are become the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne for ever and ever.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Text is <hi>the Goſpell of reinthroning God in Chriſt over the Kingdomes of this world</hi> after the great apoſtacy finiſhed: Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings fit to be publiſhed to all States,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.3.</note> that they may heare and feare, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Lord and his Chriſt, and not periſh in the day of his exaltation. All faſtings will be as <hi>Ahabs</hi> humblings untill this be done.</p>
            <p>The title of this Trumpet ſeems croſſe to the nature of the event here mentioned. It is ſtiled the <hi>third wo-Trumpet;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 11.14. V.15, 16, 17.</note> The event is Chriſts taking the Kingdoms of this world, and the triumphant ſong of the Saints celebrating this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114171:6"/>conqueſt of their Lord with prayſes. How can theſe ſuit? Very well, if we diſtinguiſh the ſubjects ſeverally concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it, which eminently are two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Antichriſt with all his creatures and confederates, and all the wicked enemies of the moſt holy God and his Saints unto theſe onely it is a Wo-trumpet, and the event is the laſt and worſt of wofull deſtructions unto them. Two conſiderations may clearly evince this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is altogether unheard of in divine revelations, that God ſhould ſound <hi>woe</hi> to his Saints. Indeed tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are their way to Heaven, and bittereſt afflictions they may ſuffer in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.19. Heb. 12.6, 10.</note> but this is a ſpeciall dignation of God to honour them, or love to chaſtiſe them unto grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter holineſſe; no <hi>wo</hi> properly ſo called, which being the effect of Gods greateſt indignation,<note place="margin">Matth. 23.13, 14, &amp;c.</note> terrifies and grindeth poore ſoules to powder.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The three laſt <hi>VVo-trumpets</hi> are directed onely <hi>to the inhabiters of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 8 13.</note> men ſo called in oppoſition to the Saints, who are <hi>Heavens people;</hi> (for by theſe names of <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> are the Antichriſtian world, and the Church of Chriſt diſtinguiſhed by the Spirit.)<note place="margin">Rev. 18.9, 11, 20.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on theſe onely is allotted that wofull ſound of this and the former Trumpets.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt and his Saints are concerned in the beſt event of this Trumpet; for in all this time of ſounding <hi>woes</hi> upon theſe earthly creatures, Chriſt is poſſeſſing the Thrones of the world, Saints are worſhipping and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God; It is therefore a <hi>joy Trumpet</hi> unto theſe. So hath God ſet the times and ſtates of creatures adverſe each to other; The worlds <hi>light</hi> is the Churches <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and the Saints <hi>joy</hi> the worlds greateſt <hi>woe.</hi> The title and event then of this Trumpet are thus reconciled.</p>
            <p>To make a clearer paſſage to the text three precogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will be uſefull. 1. Of the time. 2. Of the ſubject. 3. Of the matter of this Trumpets ſound; which I ſhall touch here but ſhortly for a generall light.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What time the ſound of this Trumpet doth concerne
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114171:6"/>is not agreed on by interpreters; ſome make it contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary with the laſt day, and ſo call it the laſt Trump;<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.16.</note> The chiefe grounds of this I ſhall take off in another place, onely for preſent, theſe reaſons evince it cannot relate to that time.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Trumpet ſounds onely a change of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this world from Lord to Lord, not the period of them which the laſt Trump of God will ſurely ſound; at the great day of judgement they ſhall all expire and be no more.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Rev. 11.18.</note> Under this Trumpet ſinne ſhall abound upon the earth, the Nations ſhall be angry at the exaltation of Chriſt and his Saints, when power ſhall be taken out of their hands; but ſuch reliques ſhall not be when the end of all things is come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Trumpet doubtleſſe foundeth <hi>woe</hi> upon the earth, and that of no ſmall continuance, which after the laſt judgement cannot be. Theſe and other conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may demonſtrate that this cannot be the laſt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet; yet by the events expreſſed in the ſucceſſive degrees of them, it may be rightly conjectured that the ſound of this ſeventh Trumpet teacheth ſomething neere to that of the laſt judgement.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others conceive more rightly that the ſound of this Trumpet concerns <hi>Heaven</hi> upon <hi>Earth,</hi> that is the ſtate of the Church below; onely the difference is, about the point of time for the beginning of theſe events ſpoken of; one pitcheth it upon the utter fall of the Weſterne myſticall <hi>Babell,</hi> and the comming of the Kings of the Eaſt, which though it muſt be under this ſeventh Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, yet is it not ſo probable to be the firſt effect of it. It is a faire gloſſe, that from the taking of the firſt Kingdom of this world out of the hand of Antichriſt, the ſound of this Trumpet ſhould be heard; for if this be a <hi>Wo-trumpet</hi> upon the Romiſh <hi>Babel,</hi> it muſt needs ſuppoſe that ſtate to be ſtanding at leaſt in the firſt ſounding of it; And the driving of Antichriſt out of the Territories and Thrones
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114171:7"/>of the world, hath been and muſt be contemporaneous with Chriſts re-entrance upon the ruling of them: So that all the Vials powred out upon the Antichriſtian ſtate in any of the Kingdomes of this world, ſeems to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporize with this Trumpet, although indeed ſeverall Scenes be acted, and the <hi>finiſhing the myſterie of God</hi> be not untill the laſt daies of the ſeventh Trumpet. This ſtate of time then ſeemeth moſt ſutable, whereof ſome portions are paſt, and ſome, and thoſe moſt glorious, are yet to come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſubject whom this Trumpet concerns, ſeemeth to be the Univerſe ſublunary, even all the Kingdomes or States in the world, which have been captivated by that Romiſh Antichriſt; therefore not <hi>England,</hi> nor the united Kingdomes of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> excluded.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The matter of this ſound and great voyces is a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation-change,</hi> of worldly Kingdomes from the power and rule of Antichriſt unto the actuall adminiſtration of the Lord and his Chriſt. In the whole paragraph about this Trumpet we have obſervable,
<list>
                  <item>1. A propoſition of the Miniſtry of this providence, wherein.
<list>
                        <item>1. The Miniſter is deſcribed, <hi>The ſeventh Angell.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. The miniſtration, <hi>He ſounded the Trumpet.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A propoſition of the effect, which is expreſt
<list>
                        <item>1. Generally, <hi>There were great voyces in Heaven, ſaying.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. Specially, wherein three effects are diſcovered,
<list>
                              <item>1. Chriſts inauguration, or the Lords reaſſuming Kingdomes for his Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 15.</item>
                              <item>2. The Saints triumphant ſong, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17.</item>
                              <item>3. The Nations anger at all this, with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out of the wrath of God to repay them, <hi>v.</hi> 18, 19.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt effect is the ſumme of the Text, to the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of which, and the certainty thereof in the Trumpets ſound, I ſhall bend the following diſcourſe. The ground
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114171:7"/>worke of all ſhall be layd in two propoſitions touching this effect.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>A Reformation-change of worldly Kingdomes to our Lord and his Chriſt, is a ſure revelation from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Lord and his Chriſt ſhall (King it) or reigne over theſe reformed Kingdomes for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The full propheſie here given is compleated in theſe two propoſitions, and both theſe will be underſtood in the opening of three main things carried in them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The true ſtate of <hi>the ſubject</hi> of this change.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The right meaning of this <hi>Reformation-change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The due account of <hi>the certainty</hi> of this Revelation.</p>
            <p>To the firſt. The ſubject of this change here ſpoken of, are the <hi>Kingdomes of the world;</hi> wherein two notions are conſiderable; one noting the nature, the other giving the ſpecification of this ſubject.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Kingdoms]</hi> note the ſubject of this <hi>Reformation-change,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>in the generall nature of it, and ſo muſt import,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The bounds of Territories which are given by God, as the <hi>continent</hi> of all men that live under government in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The people <hi>contained</hi> or inhabiting within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of ſuch Dominions muſt needs be entitled here; for not lands but ſoules, muſt be thus reformed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The chiefe of thoſe people, <hi>Princes, States,</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> among thoſe perſons ſeem eſpecially to be carried in this notion of <hi>Kingdoms;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 52.15. Iſai. 55.5.</note> and they not ſo much conſidered in themſelves, as in reſpect to government, which they are called of God to exerciſe towards others; ſo that <hi>go verning</hi> and <hi>governed</hi> as they concurre to make up King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, are here the ſubject of this reforming change.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The ſpecification of theſe Kingdomes ſets them out more fully, they are the Kingdomes <hi>of the world;</hi> ſo that what the <hi>world</hi> ſignifieth, muſt give us the ſpeciall nature of the Kingdomes mentioned; and that is uſed in a three fold acception.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As oppoſed to Heaven the ſuperiour Globe,<note place="margin">Matth. 4.8.</note> and ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114171:8"/>it muſt note <hi>Earthy</hi> Kingdomes, States, and Polities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As oppoſed to God, to Chriſt, to Grace, (as the whole world lieth in wickedneſſe) ſo it holds out wicked Kingdomes and States formerly ruled by the wicked one.<note place="margin">1 Iohn 5.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As oppoſed to particular regions or climates, and ſo it muſt ſignifie the univerſe, even all the Kingdomes of the earth; there are none excepted in the text. All theſe acceptions muſt be admitted here, and being ſo taken, the preſent ſubject cannot be doubted; The ſound of this ſeventh Trumpet then muſt needs utter things touching the Church in this life, and the Lords reſuming power over his enemies here beneath before the laſt judgement.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond. The right ſtating of this change is not of ſmall moment; for which purpoſe theſe particulars muſt be declared, 1. The terms of it. 2. The nature of it. 3. The time of it. 4. The exerciſe of it. 5. The ſtability of it, when once the Lord hath made it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Every change or motion ſuppoſeth neceſſarily two termes; one from whence the change, beginneth, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whereunto it is made: In the Text but one of theſe is named and that the laſt, <hi>the Lord, and his Chriſt;</hi> yet the other muſt needs be implied out of whoſe hands and power theſe muſt muſt be taken. Firſt then, the Lords that did King it over theſe Kingdomes of the world, were the Devil in chiefe,<note place="margin">Rev. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1, 7, 12. Revel. 17.1.</note> and his vicegerents the two beaſts, the Romiſh Antichriſt in ſpeciall, whoſe ſtate is ſhadowed by the <hi>whore</hi> who ſate upon many waters, that is, ruled over many people. Theſe onely gave laws to the States and Nations of the world,<note place="margin">revel. 13.15.</note> and required tribute from bodies and ſoules of men, and would ſet their marks upon every creature, or kill thoſe that did refuſe it. Of whoſe reign it may be noted.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Revel. 12.9.</note> The Devill was the father or authour of it in full.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Revel. 18 13.</note> Tyranny over bodies and ſoules the onely rule of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Revel. 13.8.</note> Idolatry moſt odious was the onely tribute to their King.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Revel. 19.20.</note> The end of all this government is Hell and perdition;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114171:8"/>into the lake of fire, they and all their vaſſals are thrown; from theſe cruell Lords are the Kingdomes taken.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The terme unto which this change is made is named in the Text <hi>[our Lord, and his Chriſt]</hi> Two words are here abſolute, <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and two relatives, <hi>Ours</hi> and <hi>His,</hi> all would be underſtood in their propriety.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Lord</hi> here is equivalent to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and notes God in his primitive acception of Lordſhip not derived. For indeed, there is a <hi>Lord</hi> borne, and derived, a mediating Lord, which is the Lord Jeſus, ſtiled afterward the Lords Chriſt;<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.1.</note> but here it muſt note that <hi>Lord</hi> which ſaid to <hi>Davids</hi> Lord, <hi>ſit thou on my right hand, &amp;c.</hi> God the Father more punctually, who is abſolutely Lord of Lords,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.24.</note> and King of Kings, to whom alſo the mediating Lord muſt give up his Kingdome, when his worke is done;<note place="margin">Revel. 14, 6, 7.</note> that God whom the everlaſting Goſpell holds out to be feared, to be glorifined, to be worſhipped.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The relative denoting him is <hi>Our.</hi> If it be inquired who were theſe correlates to God the King; the anſwer muſt be ſupplied, from thoſe <hi>great voyces</hi> before which ſpeak theſe words; The voyces ſay, <hi>Our Lord,</hi> and the ſame afterward utter his prayſe, and ſing his triumph for taking to him his great power to reigue; now theſe were the 24 Elders, the uſuall repreſentative body of the true Church; ſo that the true Church of Chriſt on earth is the correlate unto the Lord, the King, who are bold to ſtile him <hi>our Lord:</hi> And it not a vaine addition in this place, where it is propheſied that the Kingdomes of the world are taken into his power, and become his. How the Church is his, by election, by creation, by purchaſe, by calling, by covenant, and by profeſſion, is not now my purpoſe to relate, they are known things in the Goſpell; but the ground of the Emphaticall uſe of it here is the thing needfull to declare: Now indeed that appeares to be, that God not ſimply or abſtractively conſidered in himſelfe, but concretely and relatively known with his peculiar ones, reaſſumes theſe Kingdomes, and now
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114171:9"/>ſheweth himſelfe thus to reigne; that is, God ſo known, ſo believed, ſo worſhipped as among his choſen and true ſeed; the Kingdomes are become the Lords, as he is our God, dwelling with us, and worſhipped by us, not as miſconceived by the world For it might be ſaid he ruled in the times of Antichriſts reigne, and that the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of Antichriſt did and doe acknowledge God and Chriſt; (as ſome lukewarme advocates will plead for them) but is it God, ſo known, ſo believed on, ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, as by the true Church who cals him ours; The Sunne ſheweth the contrary; It is a falſified, corrupted, misbelieved God, that Papiſts boaſt of. In this concrete ſence <hi>Moſes</hi> writes of God triumphing over the Churches enemies,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.31.</note> 
               <hi>Their rocke is not as our rocke, the enemies themſelves being Judges.</hi> Did not many of <hi>Iſraels</hi> enemies know and confeſſe the ſame Rock or God for eſſence as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did? Yea doubtleſſe but they turned the glory of the incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible God into Images, and baſe reſemblances, and ſo made him a Rock diſtinct from <hi>Iſraels</hi> by falſe worſhip; In which reſpect <hi>Moſes</hi> ſings, God with us, and worſhipped by us, is farre above yours, he that hath ruled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed your Gods and you, as your ſelves can witneſſe. O how ſweet a thought is this, the Lord, no way but as the Churches Lord, known, and ſerved by them takes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Kingdomes of the world! The Saints can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be low, if as theirs onely God be thus exalted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The next term abſolute which denotes the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power to which theſe Kingdomes are delivered, is <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in which notion the <hi>perſon</hi> and the <hi>unction</hi> muſt be carried.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>perſon</hi> here intended is the Sonne of God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Pſalm 45.6. Heb. 1.8.</note> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Thy Throne, O God, is for ever and ever;</hi> ſo that it is one God in both expreſſions that takes unto him this power, yet ſo interpreted, God in the Mediator, God truely, God ſweetly, God ſutably held out for ruling theſe Kingdomes, even God and man.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:114171:9"/>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> of this perſon is that which the name peculiarly holds forth, and with an emphaſis in this place; the ground of this name is the annointing which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived above <hi>his fellows;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.9. Acts 10.38.</note> ſo it is ſaid, <hi>God did annoynt Jeſus of Nazareth with the Holy Ghoſt and with powers,</hi> which Unction notes his ſetting apart, and enabling for the worke of ſeverall Offices, towards the Kingdomes of his poſſeſſion. Theſe were,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Prieſtly,<note place="margin">Pſalm 110.4.</note> which was eſpecially to reconcile ſoules to God; and ſo theſe Kingdomes were taken under a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling head, which were before commanded to enmity againſt God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Propheticall,<note place="margin">Deut. 18.15.</note> wherein he was to reveale Gods will fully and ſavingly, and ſo theſe Kingdomes were to come under a ſaving Teacher, who before were ſeduced by the falſe Prophet to deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Regall,<note place="margin">Pſalm 2.6.</note> whereby he was to give laws to theſe regai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Polities,</hi> and ſet his order among them, which before were ruled by the beaſt to miſerable confuſion. All theſe make up that Chriſt, whoſe Kingdomes theſe are made at this time; and the exerciſe of their offices muſt be during the Churches imperfection in this life.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Luke 2.26. Luke 9.20.</note> The relative term ſpecifying this Chriſt is <hi>[His]</hi> that is, <hi>Jehovahs,</hi> the <hi>Lords Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Chriſt of God.</hi> It is his Chriſt, not ours, eminently declaring the Authour of this Unction; this note may perſwade not to read <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> by appoſition, as if it were the <hi>Lord Chriſt;</hi> but as diſtinct things united, and terms differently ſignifying in this place. Never theleſſe this relative addition gives ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour unto Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Nothing his Authority or Sovelaignty. Now that is Gods, Jehovah owns this Chriſty that none deſpiſe him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Teaching his truth and infallibility in all his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations; ſo that none may miſtruſt him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Shewing his irreſiſtability in regard of all the Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates in the world, that none might contend with him. This relation onely gives warrant unto poore ſoules to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114171:10"/>reſt wholly upon this Annointed, becauſe he is Gods: unleſſe he be Gods Chriſt, he muſt not be imbraced by creatures; and being his, muſt not be reſiſted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Are there then two heads conſorted in the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Kingdomes, becauſe God and his Chriſt are coupled?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not ſo, but one head onely ſpecified in this conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; the Lord and his Chriſt here, is as much as the Lord in his Chriſt, or by his Chriſt, taking to him this power over States to make them Chriſtian. God in the Mediator makes not two <hi>Lords corrivals,</hi> but one graciouſly diſpoſed to rule Kingdomes unto life;<note place="margin">John 5 22. John 12.49, 50</note> therefore the Judgement, Law, and Rule of the Father and Sonne is punctually ſaid to be one. We have ſeen the terms of this change.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond,<note place="margin">2.</note> the nature of this change, I have termed it a <hi>Reformation-change,</hi> and I conceive properly in that theſe Kingdomes are ſaid to become our Lords;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Now this ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to be made</hi> notes ſome change <hi>de nove new</hi> that was not before; for if they were the Lords be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſence here meant, they could not reaſonably be ſaid now to be made or become his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But were not all theſe Kingdomes the Lords that made them, and ſet the bounds of them from the firſt of their being? How then can they be ſaid to be made his now?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Surely this queſtion can be ſatisfied onely by the right ſtating of the preſent change, carried in that terme <hi>made</hi> the Lords. Now this in its uſe hath a double ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gen. 1.3.</note> Sometimes it notes <hi>eſſe ſimplex,</hi> the ſimple making or being of a thing which before was not, as in the creation God ſaid, <hi>Let their be light, and it was make;</hi> In this ſence it cannot here be meant, for theſe Kingdomes were made before of God, and ſo were his works.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. 7.4.</note> Sometimes it notes <hi>eſſe relativum,</hi> a relative being, as the wife is ſaid to be <hi>made her husbands;</hi> ſhe was before in the being of a woman, but not of a wife; ſo theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114171:10"/>were made before the beaſt and falſe Prophet did uſurpe them, but then onely were they made Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;<note place="margin">Facta ſunt. i. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerum in Chriſti poreſtarem, myran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidi diaboli, &amp; miniſtrorum ejus erepta. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z.</hi>
               </note>now this <hi>making</hi> in the Text is the change of that relation of theſe Kingdomes from that Antichriſtian u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation and tyranny, unto the government of the Lord and his Chriſt; ſo that now they are made the Lords by <hi>Reformation,</hi> which were his creation before. And this new worke is done by God in Chriſt, theſe waies.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quoad reſuſeeptimem Patentie,</hi> by reſuming the power into his hand, which he ſeemed to have layd aſide,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c. Revel. 11.17.</note> when he ſuffered Satan in Antichriſt to domineer over theſe Kingdomes, and rule them unto perdition; ſo it is ſaid in the Churches ſong, <hi>Thou haſt taken to thee thy great power, and haſt raigned;</hi> that is, now he did manifeſt himſelfe, that in what thoſe <hi>Lords</hi> had dealt proudly, he was above them, and his permiſſion was no approbation of them in their tyranicall uſurpations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quoad vindicias juris,</hi> by vindicating his right to theſe Kingdomes, which the Devill in Antichriſt had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, according to his old vaunt, All theſe are mine, and to whom I will I give them.<note place="margin">Luke 4.6.</note> That horrible practice of the Pope in uſurping Crowns, and taking upon him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them at his pleaſure, is a full proof of this. Now God at this time breaks out the Lyons teeth, makes the nations angry, and taketh theſe Kingdomes as a ſpoyle for Chriſt,<note place="margin">Pſalm 2.8.</note>to whom at firſt God had given them. A double right is that which God now vindicates, whereby theſe Kingdoms are called his. 1. <hi>Ius paternitatis,</hi> a right of paternity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all them, that he had given unto Chriſt, which were his ſeed indeed, and whom as he had redeemed,<note place="margin">Iſay 55, 5.</note> ſo now he calleth to the participation of life in Chriſt; This right is peculiar to ſome onely in theſe Kingdomes. 2. <hi>Jus Dominii,</hi> a right of Lordſhip which is his due, as well over ſlaves as children; So though he convert not ſavingly all theſe ſtates, yet he makes them take his Laws, ſerve his turne, ſet up his Ordinances, and worke his will, though in ſincerity perhaps they mean not ſo; Now this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114171:11"/>is reformation in its meaſure, though it reach not to the truth of converſion; So God moved <hi>Cyrus, Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar, Darius, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 72.10, 11. Pſal. 2.9.</note> of whom yet it cannot be ſaid they were converted. And ſuch a right is promiſed to Chriſt alſo in the Goſpel times, by which he ſhall uſe his Iron Rod as well as his Golden Scepter. No hope that all in all Kingdomes ſhould be truely converted, but that all ſhall be ſubdued,<note place="margin">Rev. 19.16, &amp;c.</note> made ſlaves, if not friends, not able to reſiſt the power of the Lords, is that which Scriptures ſpeak and we may expect.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Quoad ezercitium Dominii,</hi> by exerciſing this power and right over theſe Kingdomes that are become his; and this Lordſhip he doth exerciſe ſeverall waies</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a powerfull turning of the hearts of Princes from darkneſſe to light,<note place="margin">Mojeſtatem red dit viſibilem in ipſis regibus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da fernando &amp;c. <hi>Brightman in text.</hi>
               </note> cauſing them to conſider the things of God which they had not heard, and ſo to ſhut their mouthes from gainſaying Chriſt, and <hi>thrice exalt him</hi> in their hearts; of ſuch a reformation-change the Lord ſeems to ſpeake in that Goſpell promiſe, <hi>I will make thy Officers peace, and thy Exactors righteouſneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 52, 13, 14, 15.</note> when <hi>peace</hi> ſhall rule, and <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> exact, then the Kingdom is the Lords.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By a powerfull reſtraint upon others not truly called, chained up by the devill,<note place="margin">Revel. 20. 2. Pſalm 149.8.</note> and binding Kings, Princes, and Nobles as with fetters, that they ſhall not any longer hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lord from taking Thrones and ruling; Thus the Kingdomes of the world univerſally become the Lords. The King that is not converted ſhall be reſtrained. Thus farre appeares the nature of this <hi>Reformation-change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the third,<note place="margin">3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which is the <hi>time</hi> of this change, the voyces ſpeak as of the time paſt, ſaying, they <hi>are</hi> or <hi>were</hi> become the Lords, the <hi>time</hi> is expreſſed in this verb alſo; But now where to ſtate this time is the diffioulty, mens thoughts running divers waies. It hath been determined to be, while time the meaſure of the creatures in their changes laſteth, but the ſpeciall point of that time is now deſired; when thoſe Kingdoms begin to be the Lords. For the diſcovery whereof, I ſhall propoſe ſome help from theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114171:11"/>
            <p n="1">1. This ſeventh Angell is ſaid to ſound the third Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trumpet, which certainly did call for execution of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon the Kingdome of Antichriſt, whoſe Scepter made all the Kingdoms of the earth ſtoop unto him, who had ſubſcribed to his name, and worſhipped him; This was done by breaking the yoke of that Romiſh <hi>Tyran</hi> the Pope off from the neck of thoſe States, in which very moment the Lord tooke poſſeſſion of thoſe Kingdomes, from which by his great power he drove out that ſtrong one, the <hi>devil</hi> in that <hi>man of ſin.</hi> So that this Trumpet ſeems to contemporize with all the Vials poured out upon States formerly under Antichriſt, daſhing in pieces the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors, and turning others to be ſerviceable unto Chriſt. For however at all times God kept his ſecret ones within the Territories of <hi>Babel,</hi> who ceaſed not in all ages to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his truth, yet all this while the States and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes worſhipped the beaſt; So then the time of change of Kingdoms muſt be eminent, and from that inſtant that any State returned to ſubjection unto Chriſts Scepter in the Goſpell after the great apoſtacy, ſeems to begin the ſound of the ſeventh Trumpet; for then was it <hi>woe</hi> to that Antichriſt and his vaſſals, but <hi>joy</hi> to Chriſt and his Saints. Now no hard thing is it to looke back ſo farre as to finde out that point of time wherein Thrones began to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by Chriſt, and to entertain the Goſpell. The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Germany, Saeveland, Denmark, England, Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. may help us to know this time, when our Lord took theſe States from the Prince of darkneſſe ruling in that ſonne of perdition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Reformation-change</hi> is <hi>graduall,</hi> and is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on in ſeverall portions of time, from the turning of the firſt Kingdom to the finiſhing of the <hi>myſtery of God.</hi> That the meaning of this Trumpet-ſound ſhould be a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall ſuſception of Gods power to reign, I am perſwaded to believe from the courſe of the events; we ſee ſome King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms delivered, but not all yet, which are expected to be reſumed by Chriſt from that Roman Apoſtate; Now as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114171:12"/>God performs his prophecies, ſo are we to underſtand his meaning in them; and it is the beſt help we have rightly to conceive the Prophets ſpeaking of Chriſt to come, by ſeeing him come, and fulfilling what was written of him. I take it, the ſame help is to made uſe of concerning the propheſies of theſe times, and thoſe to come, of which the book of the <hi>revelations</hi> is full. So that, if we ſee the Lord hath taken Kingdomes of the world from Antichriſt, we have the truth of this Trumpet-ſound; and if yet more Kingdoms are ſtill under vaſſallage to him, this ſound de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares woe unto them abiding in that ſlavery, but good tidings to Gods hidden ones there, that the Lord will in his time take the prey out of the Dragons mouth, and rule himſelfe. And if ſo, then it muſt be a graduall change, from the taking of the firſt Kingdome to the reſuming of the laſt, which we ſee is partly done in many States, and in greater part yet to be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>One word yet ſeems to croſſe this interpretation of the time;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dub.</hi> Reuel. 10.7.</note> it is ſaid, <hi>In the daies of the voice of the ſeventh Angel, when he ſhall begin to ſound the Trumpet, even the myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed, &amp;c.</hi> And if in the beginning of his ſound all Kingdoms are changed together, and Gods my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie finiſhed, then it cannot be the time mentioned, but it muſt be wholy to come.</p>
            <p>To ſatisfie this ſcruple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sel.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Tim. 3 16.</note> two expreſſions here muſt be opened. 1. The <hi>myſterie of God,</hi> which notion is of various uſe; ſometimes it notes the ſecret way of God by mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of his Sonne in the fleſh, &amp;c. to make himſelfe communicable to his creatures, ſo to effect godlineſſe in them, and ſave them;<note place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note> This is the generall uſe of it, ſo is it called the myſterie of God, of the Father and of Chriſt. Sometimes it is of ſpeciall ſignification, and that two waies:<note place="margin">Eph. 3.6.</note> 1. It notes this ſecret good will of God toward all the Gentiles, to bring them into fellowſhip with himſelfe, from the firſt preaching of the Goſpell to them by the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.25, 16.</note> to the laſt by any Miniſtry. 2. It dictates this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret grace of God unto <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, the Jewes, for the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114171:12"/>bringing them in after their long abdication, to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafting into Chriſt. In this laſt ſence it is ſurely taken, and yet I think not excluding the other ſpeciall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor the generall in both, for as much as that is fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in theſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>When he ſhall begin to ſound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is the paſſage that begets the doubt, therefore the right reading of it muſt be inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and ſurely it is not neceſſary ſo to read it, <hi>when he ſhall begin to ſound,</hi> but vety properly, <hi>when he ſhall ſound;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as in ſuch lie inſtances. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Apoc. 1.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I will ſpue thee out, not onely begin to do it. 2 Kings. 4.1.</note>and ſo is it read by good Interpreters as one word in the future tence; which if allowable (as there is no doubt) the ſcruple is gone; for then the ſence is, that in the daies of this Angels ſounding, not in the beginning, but within the compaſſe of them, the myſtery of God ſhall be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, which is included in the former ſtate of this time. Or if you read it, <hi>when he ſhall begin to ſound,</hi> we know that expreſſion doth not alwaies note the entrance of a State, but the continuance of it, as beginning to reigne with <hi>our Tongue,</hi> is to reigne in the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> There is yet another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this with the context, which from a conjunction of finiſhing the myſterie of God with the Angels ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeems reaſonable; it is thus, The Angell that ſtood upon the Sea and Earth, ſwore by him that liveth for ever and ever, that <hi>Time ſhall he no more;</hi> that is, the time of the Papall Antichriſtian Monarchy, and of the former perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting enemies of the Saints,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ed. Compher. Bez.</note> 
               <hi>But in the daies of the voice of the ſeventh Angel, when he ſhal ſound the Trumpet, and the my ſterie of God he finiſhed,</hi> then time ſhall be; that is, the time of Chriſts triumph, and his Saints proſperity and joy; ſo that thus this 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe is part of the Angels oath concerning the not being and the being of time; though the latter be not expreſſed in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, yet it is an Ellipſis or defect not unuſuall in a continued ſpeech, this being ſo taken. However a ſufficient reply is made to the doubt in the former interpretation, if this reading be not allowed This compleating of Gods myſterie is not to be expected in the inſtant of beginning this ſound, but in the daies of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114171:13"/>its duration, the end whereof will accompliſh all the will of God concerning his Churches among Jewes and Gentiles here on Earth.</p>
            <p>To the fourth particular, which is the exerciſe of this <hi>Reformation</hi> after theſe Kingdomes are become the Lords and his Chriſts,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>(He ſhall reigne, or Ring it:)</hi> The Lord in his Chriſt deems it not enough to be a King, but to act the King in the Dominions which he takes as his own. Its the blurre of creatures to be Kings in place and ſhew, and yet not to <hi>King</hi> it, nor be able to act aright; Chriſt <hi>Kings</hi> it in truth where he hath the Throne.</p>
            <p>Two Queries will be put in:
<list>
                  <item>1.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Q.</hi> 1.</note> What is his acting as King?</item>
                  <item>2.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Q.</hi> 2.</note> How he acts it?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To the firſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mic. 5.2. Matth. 2.6. Revel. 12 5. Jer. 3.15. Jer. 23.4, 5, 6.</note> He acts the Paſtor or the good Shepheard in feeding, providing good paſture for the Kingdomes which he rules; ſuch Kings God promiſed his people when he would doe them good; but above all, this <hi>King,</hi> to rule them; <hi>I will ſet up ſhepheards over them which ſhall feed them, and they ſhall feare no more, nor be diſmayed, neither ſhall they be lacking, ſaith the Lord. Behold the daies come, ſaith the Lord, I will raiſe unto David a righteous branch, &amp;c.</hi> This is the King Chriſt who ſhall ſave his Kingdomes, and make his people dwell ſafely; He ſcatters not his flock, nor drive them away, nor hurries them, nor hunts them with dogs, as former Lords did, but acts the good ſhepheard, and they go in and out by his voyce,<note place="margin">John 10 9.</note> and finde paſture.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Iſai. 31.22.</note> He Acts the <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> this is the work of a King; ſo is it promiſed to be the acclamations of Kingdomes made the Lords, <hi>The Lord is our Iudge, the Lord is our Lawgiver, the Lord is our King, he will ſave us.</hi> They acknowledge and he doth it; He gives Laws holy and good, even all the righteous commands of his Father concerning mans way to eternall life; no unrighteous decrees, nor bitter grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces nor oppreſſing edicts, but Statutes and Ordinances, by which they may live. Thus he Kings it ſweetly.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> He acts the <hi>Iudge</hi> in all theſe Dominions, and divideth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114171:13"/>equally to all according to their wayes: He condemnes the <hi>Lie</hi> and juſtifieth the <hi>Truth;</hi> He commendeth the good and ſmiteth the evill doer; He judgeth righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>between the fat and the leave Cattell;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 34.20.</note> hee breaks the oppreſſor, and ſaves the innocent ones. Thus hee was acknowledged before, <hi>Jehovah is our Judge;</hi> and thus it is propheſied of him, <hi>He ſhall execute judgement and juſtice in the earth.</hi> He calleth not <hi>light</hi> darkneſſe,<note place="margin">Jer. 23.5.</note> nor darkneſſe light; Hee juſtifieth not the wicked for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, neither condemnes the righteous.<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>With righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall he judge the poore, and reprove with equity for the meek of the earth, &amp;c.</hi> Thus hee reignes in his repoſſeſſed Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond.<note place="margin">An. 2.</note> How hee Acts thus in his regained kingdomes, whether in his own perſon againe manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the fleſh, or in and by ſuch perſons whom he ma uſe for this work? I conceive not by his viſible, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall preſence; this is moſt likely to be done in ſuch Vice gerents as he ſhal make choice of: I propoſe theſe conſiderations to be weighed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is no neceſſity of underſtanding this rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>(He)</hi> concerning his owne perſon viſibly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; for God himſelfe hath been ſaid to reigne in his Miniſtring Rulers, and their Kingdomes have been ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods, ſo long as his feare hath been upon them,<note place="margin">Obad, v. 21. Pſal. 22.28. Pſ.71. 1, 2, &amp;c.</note> and his Law ruled in them. So <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was the Lords, and hee reigned in them and by them. This hath been the Language of God, to owne the kingdomes of his ſervants, and their government as directed by him; Nay ſometimes to reigne,<note place="margin">Dan. 4, 32.</note> when his enemies are upon the Throne: why it ſhould not bee here, I finde no forcing reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the ſound of this Trumpet be already begun, as the truth of the event already paſt in ſome degree may perſwade; then ſome Kingdomes are Chriſts already, and he reignes, though hee be ſtill at the right hand of the Father, by thoſe Rulers whom hee ſets up. His are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114171:14"/>the Kingdomes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.7.</note> becauſe he orders Kings and States by his Lore; and that ſo ſtill he may doe, without his own viſible appearance on earth, is more then probable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo in ſight already.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Not one circumſcribed Kingdome is ſaid here to be the compaſſe of his Territories, but all the Kingdomes of the earth to be his; Now if hee ſhould appeare on earth, his viſible preſence cannot bee in all Kingdomes; His body can be but in a place fit for a body; therfore is it at the right hand of God, and cannot be every where preſent, as <hi>Ubiquitaries</hi> ſenſeleſly have dreamed: Or if he be eminently preſent in one Region as a mighty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, by his Deputies ruling all other Provinces; Yet then he muſt be ſaid to reigne in others. And how much ſafer it is, to let him alone at Gods right hand, and thence to ſay hee reignes by his ſpirit in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world, I leave unto Chriſtian reaſon to judge.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It ſeemes to reaſon a very great derogation from the glory of our Lord in his Chriſt, to ſuppoſe him to leave the right hand of the Majeſty on high, to come here and ſway an earthly Scepter, whether in one or all Kingdomes of the world: for heaven now is his Throne, and the earth his Foot-ſtoole; and if he ſhould turne his Foot-ſtoole to a Throne, it were very ſtrange. However that from Heaven hee ſhall viſibly appeare to judge the quick and dead,<note place="margin">Acts i. 11. Acts 3.21. Acts 17.31</note> though not to dwell here in an earthly ſtate with the Saints, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe affirme. And this account may ſuffice concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the manner of his <hi>Reigne</hi> in the Kingdoms of this world.</p>
            <p>To the fifth and and laſt thing,<note place="margin">5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pſal. 33.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pſal. 17.2.5. Eph. 3.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and laſt thing about this <hi>Reformation-change,</hi> which is the <hi>ſtability</hi> of it, we are now come, <hi>For ever and ever</hi> ſhall this King reigne: The phraſe here ſeemeth ſynonomous with that <hi>Hebrew</hi> expreſſion, <hi>to generation and generation,</hi> and <hi>throughout all generations.</hi> Sometimes the word is uſed ſimply, <hi>for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114171:14"/>ever</hi> without repetition, and then frequently notes abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute eternity; but in this kind of doubling many times leſſe, onely duration of ſome ages or an aeviternity as it is called: The Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth an Age, or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, among other things, and ſo here doubled in the plurall <hi>to ages of ages,</hi> is the continuance of the ages or generations of this world, ſo that ſuch is the ſtable duration of this reigne of Chriſt over theſe Kingdomes even ſo long as the ages of theſe doe continue. Three things are carried in this expreſſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Progreſſe in his reigne from age to age, He ſhall goe forward, proſper and grow in his Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Immutability of State, ſo ſhall he <hi>King</hi> it, that theſe Kingdomes ſhall not change their Lord, nor any more retreat to Antichriſt as in the great Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, when once the Lord hath reſumed theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Eternity of duration, ſo long as theſe Kingdomes laſt, even for that ever and ever, our Lord and his Chriſt ſhall reigne, making friends, or keeping under ſlaves: Then the end of the Mediators Kingdome ſhall come, and God that was from everlaſting ſhall rule to everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in whom the hope of all Saints ſhall be perfected. So farte to the ſtate of this Reformation-change.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt generall to be held out is the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all this Revelation, what that is, that we may have a ſure ground for faith to worke upon concerning theſe matters, which I ſhall labour by ſome ſpeciall conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations about the context to make cleare.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Author of this Revelation, it is our Lord himſelfe in his Chriſt; ſo it is ſaid in the entrance of this Book, <hi>The Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt which God gave unto him to ſhew unto his ſervants.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 1.1.</note> Now God cannot deceive, nor be deceived; if he be the Author, Infallibility is upon the word. There is one name men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the doxologie of the Church upon this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation peculiar unto God, which muſt ſatisfie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114171:15"/>creatures concerning the truth of this event, if ſpoken by God,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.4. Rev. 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>It is He that is, and Hee that was, and He that is to come.</hi> It is <hi>He</hi> that can alwayes ſay, <hi>I am.</hi> If hee had not been from eternity, if he bee not now, or if he ſhould not be to eternity, juſt cauſe there might bee of miſtruſting his Revelation; but if hee was to make all things that have been, and if he bee to make things that are, and if hee ſhall bee to make all things to come in his owne time, there can bee no ground of ſuſpecting him. Thus the Church looketh on him and is comforted. Indeed were hee of yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and muſt hee ceaſe againe, his Revelation could not over-value the <hi>Delphick</hi> Oracle; but this is his ſtrong reaſon to be believed as God, <hi>He was, and is, and is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The meanes of revealing this is not deſpicable, it was by an Angel:<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> whether ſo in Nature, as a miniſtring Spirit ſent out for comforting Gods choſen in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as I rather conceive;<note place="margin">Rev. 3.1, &amp;c.</note> or ſo onely in Office, and then a <hi>Man,</hi> a ſpeciall Meſſenger, or Miniſter expreſſed in this viſion, as it may be; Yet it is Gods owne meanes of his owne ſending to declare, and therefore none of a doubtfull call, that hee ſhould bee ſuſpected; by <hi>John</hi> it is com to us, and he had it from Chriſt this whole viſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The clearneſſe of the <hi>Revelation</hi> adds more ſtrength to its certainty;<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.19.</note> It comes not like a whiſpering, or muttering of ſeducing ſpirits out of the earth, but ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a <hi>Trumpet</hi> from heaven;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.8.</note> and Gods Trumpet giveth ſurely a diſtinct ſound, that wee may underſtand his minde in it, and ſute our ſelves to his will. So it did in declaring wrath and warre againſt ſinners,<note place="margin">Amos a. 6. Hoſ. 8.1. Zech. 9.14.</note> that they might beleeve and tremble, and returne; So alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing his grace in Chriſt towards his people: the Trumpet ſounds it, that poore ſoules might heare and beleeve, and be comforted. A trumpet-Revelation then from God needs not to be ſuſpected: A loud, eminent,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114171:15"/>diſtinct diſcovery doth God make of theſe viſions, that as they are ſure in themſelves, ſo they might bee ſurely knowne and received by his Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſweet gratulations and doxology of the Church recorded in the context,<note place="margin">Rev. 11, 16, 17</note> muſt conclude the certainty of the event: It is incredible that God would give a viſion of praiſe to mock himſelfe withall, and that hee ſhould receive bleſſing for that which is not, nor was ſure ever to be: The certainty of praiſe argueth undenyably the certainty of this gracious event.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The experience of ſo many Kingdoms and States al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready delivered from the yoke of Antichriſt, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from that great Apoſtaſie to entertain the true Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of Gods Son, may perſwade, that the reſidue of the promiſe to be performed is as ſure as that part already accompliſhed in theſe 100 yeares paſt, which wee ſee with our eyes. Experience therefore ſhould ſtrengthen faith, and breed an aſſured hope in Gods people of the Lords more glorious appearing, to take more Kingdoms of the world into his power; that they may mightily ſtrive to it, and patiently wait for it. This hope ſhall not make us aſhamed. Thus the doctrine is opened, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed: The Uſe followes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To inform us in ſome truths depending;<note place="margin">Uſe <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> their Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries doe iſſue from the ſound of this Trumpet opened unto us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If Kingdoms of the world ſhall have ſuch a <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation-change,</hi> as to be taken from Antichriſt, &amp; ſubdued to our Lord and his Chriſt, then it muſt follow,<note place="margin">Corol. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Kingdoms may be, and are the Subjects of Reformation, though not the adequat ſubjects of true Converſion.</hi> The underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the true ſtate of <hi>Reformation,</hi> as well as the viſible ſtate of <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> which already are become the Lords, will ſufficiently cleare this inference.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reformation</hi> is a terme not freequently uſed by our Tranſlators, I remember it but twice,<note place="margin">1. Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and in two different acceptions.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114171:16"/>
            <p n="1">1. As reſpecting the matter or object about which Reformation is; And in this ſenſe mainely is the word tranſlated from the Apoſtles expreſſion to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as the conſideration of the context will make cleare.<note place="margin">Heb. 9.1, 10.</note> The ſpirit there labours to convince the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, that by the Meſſiah Gods mind was, the whole Jewiſh Tabernacle muſt be throwne downe, that is, their Church frame in all externall Ordinances; He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the Tabernacle with the adjoyned ordiances and ſervices, which, ſaith he, were impoſed, <hi>untill the time of Reformation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Of what? Surely not of hearts, but of that Church frame and ordinances, which were but figures for that time preſent, putting thoſe which were true, ſpiritual &amp; heavenly in their places. The word here rendred reformation ſignifieth <hi>A thorough-right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of all things in the Church in order to eternall life. This Chriſt did, by removing things ſhaken of God, that is, all <hi>ſhadow-workes</hi> formerly in the Church, in Prieſt-hood,<note place="margin">heb. 10.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Sacrifice, and other ſervices, all ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to life, and by eſtabliſhing things unſhaken, the true <hi>image-works</hi> of heaven,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> lively drawne, Prieſt-hood, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, ſervices, &amp;c. by which men might certainly be brought to God, and live. This perrectification of Chriſts then is of meanes tending to heaven, that men might ſee the right line directing unto God, in the right uſe of which they may be ſaved: It is a Reformation for hearts indeed but not of hearts; for this reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may truely be in a Kingdome, and is where the true Prieſt-hood of Chriſt, Sacrifice, and ſpirituall ſervices, are ſet up and maintained; though hearts for the moſt part may not be ſavingly converted to God by them. The point of time in the Text evidences this to be an <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance-reformation,</hi> not an <hi>heart one;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. a ſingular.</note> for it was a ſingle ſpeciall time, even the ſpace of laying this Church-frame by Chriſt in his Apoſtles, and no longer, the whole worke of this reformation was diſpatched then, but the time of heart-reformation is in all ages; therefore thoſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114171:16"/>times are not that, nor this worke that. Kingdomes then are reformed after Chriſt, when his true ordinances are eſtabliſhed and ſubmitted unto, and falſe Antichriſtian conſtitutions are driven out, though few hearts in truth may be changed to God by them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reformation</hi> in our uſe reſpects the perſon or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in whom the power of God may be manifeſt for changing the man according to his mind revealed in former ordinances, thus we read it uſed by our Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <hi>If ye will not be reformed by theſe things, &amp;c.</hi> In the letter it is read,<note place="margin">Levit. 26.23; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>If ye will not be chaſtiſed to me by theſe things, &amp;c.</hi> That is, if by theſe meanes, your hearts be not turned to me; So that, here the reformation of the man muſt be intended, And that wee know may be two wayes: 1. In truth, when Chriſt is formed truely on the Soule. 2. In ſhew, when the outward man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes to theſe conſtitutions of God. Kingdomes may be ſo reformed as to yeeld outward obedience to the Scepter of Chriſt, though few hearts have the true Image of God imprinted on them: And thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed doe Kingdomes become the <hi>Lords,</hi> when they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the lyes of Antichriſt, and cleave to the truth of Chriſt, though but in outward deportment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Kingdomes of the world are ſaid to bee the Lords, but indeed they neither have beene, nor are,<note place="margin">2. Kingdomes.</note> nor ſhall be all by true converſion, yet they muſt be by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; No Kingdome that ever was called the Lords on earth had all Saints in it, nor ever ſhall, if Chriſt have propheſied truely, That the laſt day ſhall find men, as the Flood found the world in <hi>Noahs</hi> daies;<note place="margin">Marth. 24.36, 37, &amp;c.</note>yet ſurely ſhall Kingdomes be the Lords, and that muſt be by Reformation as declared, not by true ſaving con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; And to ſay, that ſuch a Kingdome of Chriſt <hi>England</hi> is, I ſuppoſe is conſonant to the voyce of this Trumpet.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If Kingdomes muſt be our Lords, that is, Chiefe States, Kingly and Ruling Powers, this teacheth us,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114171:17"/>
               <hi>States and worldly Powers Chriſt will make uſe of to ſet up his glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Corol. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they are not utterly inconſiſtent with his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall deſignes.</hi> Antichriſt indeed had them, and made uſe of them for his owne purpoſe, but therefore Chriſt will not utterly refuſe them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note> God himſelfe was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of theſe orders of men, thereby purpoſing to make one helpfull to another for reaching his owne glory; And Satan in this as other things was Gods <hi>Ape</hi> to make uſe of them, but his enemy, to corrupt Princes and great men of the earth to increaſe his owne King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; therefore perſwaded he them to give their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the Antichriſtian Beaſt,<note place="margin">Revel. 17.13.</note> and to make poore ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects by their Tyrannicall perſecutions to doe ſo too, that they might be damned together. But now in the reſtitution of all things the Lord Chriſt re-poſſeſſeth theſe Principalities againe, as a needfull order of men, inſtituted by God, though corrupted by Satan, and makes uſe of them for his high and ſpirituall ends to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his worke upon the earth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By putting into their hearts to ruine that great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of grace, the <hi>myſticall Babilon,</hi> the Mother of Harlots, and of all abominations, as well as all ſpirituall and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall wickedneſſe.<note place="margin">Revel. 17.16.17.</note> So it is written, <hi>The Kings ſhall hate the whore, and make her deſolate and naked, and eate her fleſh and burne her with fire, For God hath put it into their hearts to fulfill his will, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By making them ſhields of the earth, a defence unto his ordinances and people,<note place="margin">Pſal. 47.9. Iſay 49.23. 1 Tim. 2.2.</note> and nurſing Fathers and Mothers to his Saints, that under them and by them godlineſſe may be perfected in his Churches. If theſe Scepters be our Lords, doubtleſſe they are ſo, not as <hi>Lords,</hi> but as <hi>Servants</hi> miniſtring for him, which he would not owne, were they not appointed of God, and ſo needfull to helpe on his worke among men.</p>
            <p>But Chriſts worke is <hi>heart-worke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obj.</note> what can Princes doe to ward that?</p>
            <p>For anſwer,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> let it be conſidered; 1. All Chriſts work
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114171:17"/>is not <hi>heart-worke,</hi> much of it is upon the outward man by reſtraint and otherwiſe, in this the power of the word may be inſtrumentall, being made the Lords 2. Gods outward ordinances were intended to make way to mens ſpirits, his <hi>Rod,</hi> as well as his <hi>Word;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 6.9.</note> the <hi>Preacher</hi> hath no more <hi>ſelfe-power,</hi> nor <hi>ordinance-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> than the <hi>Prince,</hi> God makes the Word effectuall, and ſo he hath done the Sword upon a <hi>Manaſſeh-ſpirit.</hi> 3. The Rod for the fooles back is Gods ordinance,<note place="margin">Prov. 19.29.</note> as well as the Word to the obedient eare: who ſo deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth either, ſinneth againſt that light of nature,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.12</note> whereby the Gentiles were condemned.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt did not make uſe of them,<note place="margin">Obj.</note> nor his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, at the laying of the foundation of the Goſpell; the Kingdomes of the world were then againſt him: how ſhould they be helpefull now?</p>
            <p>I returne thus: 1.<note place="margin">Sol.</note> Our Lord made uſe of them before that time, and owned theſe Kings and Kingdomes by whom his name was exalted,<note place="margin">Pſal, 18.1, &amp;c.</note> and no where hath be ſince rejected his owne ordinance. 2. At that time of Chriſts comming in the fleſh, God by his Prophets had fore-told the ſtate of, enmitie, which the great Roman Monarchy and all the Kingdomes of the earth with him ſhould expreſſe againſt his Some, therefore no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, he made no uſe of them at that time, for it was one time given to the Devill to rule in them,<note place="margin">Act. 41, 27, 22.</note> and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them to crucifie the Lord of glory, which <hi>Gods, counſell determined to be done;</hi> but with more righteous and gracious thoughts than they intended. 3. That was not the time wherein God had appointed to take to himſelfe his great power and to raigne; but now the time is come that he hath taken Kingdomes to rule in and by them, and make his lawes their lawes. 4. In that, very time of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, would I but require this, ought not the <hi>Caſers</hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> himſelfe to have advanced the Lord and his Chriſt, and have uſed their power to bring their ſubjects in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114171:18"/>to him, and to have ruled by his truth? Shall not God laugh them to ſcome, and they periſh in his wrath becauſe they did not? I believe they will have no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate for them. If ſo, then let Chriſtians argue <hi>de jure,</hi> what Rulers ought to have done then; not <hi>de facte,</hi> what they did; and if it were the Magiſtrates dutie then to rule men to God in Chriſt, it is no leſſe now; And ſinfull practice is no good preſident againſt Divine right.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If this Trumpet ſound the greateſt <hi>Woe</hi> upon all Kingdomes under the Devill and Antichriſt, and the greateſt <hi>Joy</hi> to the Kingdomes under God and Chriſt, this is rightly inferred,<note place="margin">Corol. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The beſt</hi> Criſis <hi>or judgement of Kingdome? Weale or Woe, it by the Lord that ſwayeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them.</hi> If Satan, if Antichriſt, if wicked Lords, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is that State; If God, if Chriſt, if holy Princes and Governours, bleſſed is that Kingdome. O the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Machiavillian O the folly of humane policy! <hi>Germany</hi> hath its intereſt, and Spaine, and <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> theirs, one in alies, another in treaſures, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in hearts of Subjects, &amp;c. And ſuppoſe all theſe kept at any time, or poſſible to be kept, have they ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any Kingdome, or can they, that it ſhall not periſh at the breath of Gods mouth? How hath God befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the counſells of the wiſeſt Politicians in all ages, and yet are we ſeeking for Kingdomes ſafetie and glory within the creatures Spheare? To have one Lord in Chriſt our King, were a proſpering and ſecuring wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome beyond all under the Saline. Did ever a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome keeping its <hi>Imeroſt</hi> in God periſh? Obedience to the Lord and his Chriſt in all his diſcoveries, is the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-intereſt of any Common-Wealth;<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.15. <hi>Sapores</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> to <hi>conſtintius</hi> the Emperor. Iſay. 14.12. Obad. v. 4.</note> O <hi>bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord!</hi> What though Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs of the Earth write themſelves <hi>Brothers of the Sunue and of the Moone, fellow of the Starres,</hi> yet heare what the moſt high ſaith, O <hi>Lucifer, ſonne of the morning, how art thou cut downe?</hi> And, <hi>though thou ſet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114171:18"/>thy neſt among the Starres, thence will I bring thee down.</hi> What can a mount to the Starres helpe poore creatures, when the breath of the Lord bloweth them downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? One true intereſt in out Lord and his Chriſt, would proſper and perpetuate a Kingdome, and honour Princes above the Satrres; of ſuch would the moſt high ſay, <hi>Yee are Gods and Sounes of the muſt high:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note> of ſuch Kingdomes no end ſhould be but of perfection. Let us then judge of our <hi>Wealth</hi> by how much we are the Lords, and of our <hi>Woe</hi> by ſo much as we are not his, or refuſe him. Theſe are the Corolaties.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Uſe <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> If this Trumpet ſound forth joy onely to the holy people, and the Kingdomes that are <hi>our Lords,</hi> and ſo farre indeed as they are the <hi>Lords,</hi> the wofull ſound of it muſt concerne the Kingdomes which are not his, and all Polities ſo far as they are not Chriſts; ſo that, well may a lamentation be taken up by them and for them; Is there not cauſe, when Chriſt owne's not State, nor States him? It's true, that in the execution of all the dreadfull <hi>Woes</hi> upon the Romiſh Babel, when the Kings and Merchants of the earth are bemoaning her deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Saints are called to rejoyce over her;<note place="margin">Revel. 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>Rejoyce over her thou Heaven, and ye Holy Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, for God hath avenged you on her:</hi> But when <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuels Land</hi> ſhall in any part break. Chriſts yoke, reſiſt their Lord, provoke him to diſpleaſure, and themſelves to waſting, who can refraine from teares? It calls a dead <hi>Grand-mother</hi> out of her grave to weepe,<note place="margin">Jer. 31.15.</note> 
               <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi> was heard weeping in <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> time and would not be comforted: Why? For her children once own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God had ſinned, and were not. <hi>Jadah</hi> was <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuels Land,</hi> and upon like grounds <hi>England</hi> may; if this State will not ſuffer the Lord to <hi>King</hi> it over them,<note place="margin">Iſay. 8.18.</note> as they once refoſed, an Aſſyrian Lord, a dreadfull Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor the Rod of Gods anger, may have commiſſion to paſſe thorow, and goe over, and ſtretch his wings to the breadth of our Land; This will be grievous, when
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114171:19"/>the iron Scepter of wicked Tyrants ſhall teach us how ſweet the Government of Chriſt was, which wee have deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>Symptoms of this wofull ſound are the graduall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of a people or State from the Lords Rule. That the people have gone a Whoring from God, by ſpirituall and corporall uncleanneſſe, and the little cauſe of <hi>Englands</hi> rejoycing in it,<note place="margin">By M. <hi>T. Caſe on Hoſ. 9.1.</hi>
               </note> ye have heard ſufficiently declared in the morning for our humiliation. I confeſſe, I hould have wondred at ſuch ſevere propheſying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>this kind of filthineſſe,</hi> what the reaſon of it might be, but that I ſee ſo many characters of uncleane hearts viſible on their bodies, and have beene certainly informed of moſt abominable <hi>Inceſts</hi> in ſeverall parts of the Kingdome and eſpecially in the Countie of <hi>Kent</hi> not farre remote,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>A. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of it.</note> 
               <hi>where the ſonne hath married his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife,</hi> and as is beleeved, <hi>ſhe was with child by him, while his father lived.</hi> Theſe are evills intolerable in the ſates of morall Pagans, much more inconſiſtent with that Kingdome where the Lord rules. Will ye be pleaſed this day to be humbled for theſe abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and put out the power which Chriſt hath given you to cleanſe the Land from theſe and ſuch like abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We ſhall then hope our Lord will not refuſe to owne us; but otherwiſe, that he ſhould deale with the Land as with an whoriſh woman,<note place="margin">Ezech. 23.25. &amp;c.</note> ſlit her noſe, and ſtrip her naked, and ſpit in her face, and give her to death, is all that can be expected. No more of this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall State, my labour is ſaved by the mornings worke, I ſhould rather crave leave to diſcharge the dutie of a faithfull Miniſter of Chriſt unto you, being now called, I look upon you as a State and chiefe Power of Chriſt in this Kingdome; ſo far as you the Lord, and he rules in you, ſo much cauſe have his people to rejoyce; and ſo farre as any defection appeares from that Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, ſo much <hi>VVoe</hi> is pronounced upon you, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Land. The ſaddeſt <hi>Omen</hi> is when in Head and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114171:19"/>Rulers Chriſt <hi>Kings</hi> it not. I am not come with Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations upon out <hi>Truely VVorthies,</hi> the ſearcher of hearts knowes, I deſire nothing but true Honour from God upon you, and that muſt bee by his ruling in you, and your ruling by and for him: Onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viations from this proclaime <hi>woe;</hi> and it will be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to let you heare the generall voices of the Land about you, to vindicate your Honour where it is cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſely ſtained, and to be humbled for any defection from Chriſt in the ſtate appearing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Its lamentable with a <hi>ſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> when fooliſh, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, wicked, and ungodly <hi>Steeres-men</hi> ſit at the <hi>Helm</hi> to ſway it. As wiſe a King and Stateſ-man as the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of men knew, by the wiſedome of God gave theſe dictates, <hi>Woe to thee ô Land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 10.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>when thy King is a child, and thy Princes eate in the morning. Bleſſed art thou, O Land, when thy King is the Son of Nobles, and thy Princes eat in due ſeaſon, for ſtrength and not for drunkenneſſe.</hi> See the <hi>Woe</hi> and Weale of States. Happy Land whoſe King is innobled by God, and Princes made gracious, and taught by him even to the uſe of meate and drinke: there <hi>our Lord</hi> hath the Kingdome and his <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But <hi>woe</hi> to that State, where a King, a childe, a foole ſhall reigne, an enemy to the Lord; and Princes luſtfull, gluttonous, drunken, and laſcivious, ſuch as muſt have a breakfaſt every morning in ſinne, ſhall ſteere by their Counſailes, Chriſt is no Law-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there. This is woefull,<note place="margin">Prov. 19 2.</note> 
               <hi>The people muſt mourns when the wicked beareth rule.</hi> They ſay there are ſuch among you, if I may ſpeak in uſuall termes, Impious, childiſh, cock-pit Counſellors: If ſo, ſuch are bad Truſtees for Lawes, Liberties, and Religion; A <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> or <hi>Spartan-State</hi> would provide againſt ſome of thoſe, and not hazzard Kingdomes in the hands of fooles; much more ſhould that State which is Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. I know yee are not Electors, but the Scumme of People lend ſuch unto you, and will ſpoyle all your boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114171:20"/>unleſſe you take it off. It is a voice of feare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that love you and pray for you in the Weſt and other parts, that ſuch as could not overcome you by the Sword, labour to doe it by Votes, even by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch as will Vote God from among you. <hi>Ever Honoured Worthies,</hi> ſee if it bee ſo, let the ſight of one root of bitterneſſe among you humble you; And now ſhew forth Chriſt ruling in you: Methinks its poſſible for a Chriſtian Parliament by a Law to purge &amp; prevent ſuch profane Paganiſh leaven, and to honour Chriſts Kingdome ſo much, as to make groſſe ſinne uncapable of a Memberſhip among you. Surely, if that be allowed, our Lord rules not, and this is woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's lamentable with a Kingdomes, where the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the poore are grinded,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.14, 15</note> and the cauſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, Winddow and Friendleſſe, ſlighted and not heard. The Lord in his Chriſt gives better Lawes, and will require them,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.17. Deut, 10.18</note> 
               <hi>Judge for the Fatherleſſe, plead for the VVidow.</hi> God doth this himſelfe, therefore will have his Vice-gerents doe like to him. It is a fame, that yee are profuſe in giving to the full ſonle, while the hungry and friendleſſe, which have ſpent and been ſpoyled of all for the cauſe of God in your hands, are ſome of them ready to periſh for bread. See after this, our Lord will not doe ſo: let not this (Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and beloved) be miſtaken; neither I nor any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heart can grutch the due rewards of noble-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpirits in theſe times. My heart is towards the Governours that offered themſelves willingly to the worke of God; my thoughts (I am perſwaded) are the ſame with all thoſe worthy ſouls, who deſire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with God. Let the hungry bee fed, and naked cloathed, and fatherleſſe ſuſtained, and widow comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and well deſerving men not unrewarded. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there will abide a <hi>woe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It's lamentable with a Kingdome, where judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114171:20"/>by Bribery or otherwiſe becomes vendible, and juſtice is bought and ſold. So <hi>Jeremiah</hi> thought, ſo <hi>Micah</hi> preached, <hi>The head judge for reward, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Jer. 5.31. Mic. 3.11, 12. Deut. 10.17.</note> therefore ſhall Zion be plowed as a field.</hi> Our Lord takes no reward in Judgement, neither muſt the Stewards that act for him; ſuch as doe he curſeth. The voice of people is, there is ſuch a fault among you. I confeſſe it is incredible to mee, that ſuch a <hi>Judge</hi> as a <hi>Parliament,</hi> conſiſting of ſo many heads can bee the ſubject of ſuch corruption, and I am confident the body is free in judging: But it is replyed, though the judgement at laſt come free, yet motions many times coſt men deare. I cannot charge it upon any, and I wiſh that they who complaine, would teſtifie to the faces of the guilty at your owne Barre. I am confident the juſt hands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you would be againſt ſuch a man, to thruſt him out of your Aſſembly. But yet renowned Patriots, look into this matter; And to confute the world, every one of you that deſire to act for God in your admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, take the juſt complaints of the poor and oppreſſed, communicate to your body, and proſecute righteous cauſes freely as your owne. This will be a Character of the Lord upon the Throne. The neglect will prove a deviation from Chriſt, and breed ſo much <hi>woe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It's lamentable for that State, where Juſtice is delayed. Our Lord ownes not this; His command is to the houſe of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer, 21.12.</note> 
               <hi>execute judgement in the morning;</hi> now that will paſſe away quickly, therefore juſtice muſt ſpeedily be done. It is a tryed truth in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, <hi>A juſt ſentence delayed hath more oppreſſed, then an unrighteous dispatch could have done.</hi> They that hang about your doores, and ſuch as have waited long for ſentence, enemies and friends ſay, it is thus with you. I know great affaires and difficult have been and are upon your hands that may hinder quick diſpatches, and great Bodies can move but ſlowly, and it may
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114171:21"/>anſwer much for you. But (yee Rulers of God) bee active, ſeek no delayes, Judge while it is morning; If yee doe not, ſo farre yee deny the government of the Lord, and this will be lad.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It's lamentable for a Kingdome to have perfidious and Covenant-breaking guides: Our Lord is not ſo, nor inveed may his deputies bee ſo. Hee is a God <hi>kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-Covenant,</hi> faithfull and true;<note place="margin">Neh. 9.32. Deut. 4.23.</note> and hee leaves the charge upon all his to doe ſo: Yet it is Printed to the world, That yee are all perjur'd perſons, and Covenant-breakers: I like not reproaching of Rulers, <hi>Paul</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged it Gods Words, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evill of the Ruler of thy people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 23.5.</note> He that doth ſhall ſuffer from the Lord: yet yee Chriſtian Senators, it concernes you nearely to be humbled for all ſlips of infirmity about the Covenant of your God (from which what fleſh can keep free?) and vindicate your ſelves from groſſer evills by a true juſtification, or elſe in all the Countries it may get a common faith. Weare the girdle which Chriſt weares,<note place="margin">Iſai, 11.5.</note> 
               <hi>Righteouſneſſe is the girdle of his loynes, and faithfulneſſe the girdle of his reines;</hi> Let it be yours too, and yee ſhall proſper, but unfaithfull and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Rulers, woe to them and their Kingdome, God will eaſe himſelfe of ſuch adverlaries, and avenge him of ſuch enemies. This is wofull.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It's lamentable with a State, to be remiſſe and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of Gods affaires in reforming his Houſe, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Ordinances, and giving up the Kingdome to our Lord and his will revealed, yet to be active and mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full about their owne matters. The Lord made the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning State of the Jewes ſmart for this; and he points at the matter:<note place="margin">Hag. 1.4, 5, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>It is time for your to dwell in your ſieled Houſes, and thu houſe lye waſte?</hi> Conſider, this is the reaſon, yee ſow much and bring in little, &amp;c. A woe was upon them, for they did not minde to exalt the Lord above themſelves. And the adviſe to remove it is to fall about the worke.<note place="margin">Hag. 1.8.</note> Gods <hi>Reformation worke</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:114171:21"/>was the end of his calling you together, that your affairs might thrive in the proſperity of his; for ſute Gods matters going well make the Kingdome glorious, this doth not make that. Let not God loſt the glory of the ſmall beginnings viſible toward that work: But is this laid to heart, and is it contended for as your glory? It is ſaid by ſome, that yee will never reforme up to Gods Word, though yee bee ingaged by Covenant to doe ſo. I dare not believe this, I pray for the ſtrengthning of your hands to this work, and wait working in my place, if I might there give helpe, and at laſt receive more from you, for the purging of Congregation, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the holy things of God from being defiled. Yet great <hi>Remoraes</hi> keek back the Fabrick, Carnall and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall wickedneſſes, though not tolerated by a Law, yet connived at, or not reproved as God would have them, Doctrines againſt the eternall Son-ſhip of the Mediator publiſhed, and aſſertions againſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>ſelfe-credibility</hi> of Scripture maintained; the very prime er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour that brought in the great Apoſtacy. Our Lord and his Chriſt hate ſuch things as theſe; no Lawes of his Kingdome tolerate contradictions to his owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; his prime Miniſters would not vouchſafe a <hi>God-ſpeed</hi> to ſuch as thoſe: Yet the world knowes,<note place="margin">a Joh. v. 10, 11.</note> with what ardency the toleration of thoſe and other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies as bad are ſtriven for. A timely <hi>Item</hi> may be given, An admiſſion of Doctrine deviliſh and deſtroying the ſaving revelation of God in his Sonne, is an emiſſion of Chriſt, and ſo the loſſe of him. I would not be ſeverer then God would have me againſt any that pretend Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in matters circumſtantiall, and that divide not from the <hi>head;</hi> therefore can I not cry, <hi>That nothing muſt be tolerated in leſſer differences;</hi> but this Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That the woman</hi> Jezabel <hi>muſt not bee ſuffered,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.22.</note> (who could not vent worſe lies) under leſſe paine then the loſſe of God and his Chriſt, and the ruine of Churches: And I muſt ſay, that the <hi>Toleration of all things muſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114171:22"/>be a deſtructive principle to the State or Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be allowed.</hi> Experience hath ſhewed us no leſſe in Kingdomes and Churches called by Gods Name. Theſe are only ſuggeſted, which need a larger Treatiſe to State fully. ye Servants of Chriſt, take heed of yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe pretences of Conſcience, the Devill, and not Chriſt hath his throne there; And no ſtronger hold for him than Conſcience if he once take it. Chriſt will not ſuffer him to ſhelter here, therefore ye may not, ſo much as in you lyeth; if ye doe, the Lords Trumpet ſounds <hi>Woe</hi> upon you.</p>
            <p>Doe not other States,<note place="margin">Dub.</note> as ſome of the united Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, tolerate all theſe hereſies, and protect them, and yet they proſper? Who more?</p>
            <p>I deſire not to deale with other Srates,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> unleſſe I might doe them good, I am now onely called to our owne, yet others being made exemplary, a word in ſoberneſſe and truth may not offend. I ſuggeſt onely theſe thoughts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Can any man ſay, that proſperitie is a ſign peculiar unto Truth? Then let <hi>Rome</hi> come in and ſpeake more than any for outward proſperitie.<note place="margin">Ecles. 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>No man can know the love or hatred of God by all that is before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Are not ſpirituall wickedneſſes as odious to God as carnall?<note place="margin">Gal. 5.20.21.</note> And are not theſe Hereſies ſuch which God condemnes as workes of the fleſh inconſiſtent with the Kingdome of his Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hath God made an end yet of viſiting Nations for the ſinnes of them? When God hath done judging were a better time to urge this example than now. I pray God the evill day may not overtake thoſe <hi>States;</hi> The good Lord cauſe the Cup of trembling to paſſe by them, and purge their iniquities peaceably. But I am preſſed in ſpirit to ſay,<note place="margin">1 King. 12.26, &amp;c. 1. King, 13.24. <hi>Qui non vetat peccare cum pateſt jubet.</hi> Sen.</note> God hath not ſpared ſuch State-Polities, which have ſought their own riſe by the ruine of God and his Truth. Witneſſe <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nebat,</hi> who made Iſrael to ſinne: And he bids ſinne, that doth not hinder it when he can. I feare their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114171:22"/>may begin in the day of their confederacy with <hi>Spaine.</hi> But Gods Truth, my beloved, and not mans example muſt be the rule, ſtrive up to the perfection of God. If none of theſe lyes muſt be in Heaven, it is mans dutie not to allow them on earth. If Hereſies yet muſt be, let us mourne for what we cannot helpe; It is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable neceſſitie when not allowed; it will be rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in iniquitie, either for Stute or Church wilfully to tolerate; And then beware, the third and worſt of <hi>woes</hi> which this Trumpet ſounds.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, The ſound of this Trumpet,<note place="margin">Uſe <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thence ariſing, as they ſpeake exaltation unto our Lord and his Chriſt, ſo no leſſe dutie and counſell to the States and Powers of the world.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſuch as are in vaſſalry to the Devill and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that are ſtill raging and in conſpiracy againſt the Lord and his Chriſt; The Pſalmiſts counſell is ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable for them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Be wiſe O ye Kings, be inſtructed ye Judges of the Earth; Serve the Lord with feare, and rejoyce with trembling; Kiſſe the Sone;</hi> To love and honour, and worſhip the Lord in his Chriſt, is better than to be raging and combining againſt his Annointed. 1. God will laugh at their plots, and have them in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. 2. Our Lord in his Sonne will reign, doe what they can againſt it. 3. The deſolating woes ſhall fall upon all Kingdomes that doe oppoſe, He will breake them in pieces with a Rod of Iron, and daſh them in pieces like a Potters Veſſell. It is firmely written in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of God,<note place="margin">Iſai. 60.12.</note> 
               <hi>The Nation and Kingdome that will not ſerve him ſhall periſh, ye thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</hi> O that this Trumpet might ſound in the eares of thoſe Kings and Kingdomes that yet give their power to the Romiſh Beaſt!</p>
            <p n="2">2. To thoſe States whom our Lord and his Chriſt hath reſcued out of that ſlavery, and made them his owne Dominions, among whom our own may be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, Thus the voyces ſay:</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:114171:23"/>
            <p n="1">1. Bleſſe the Lord in the beauties of holineſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the great worke that he hath done, that he hath taken to him his great power, and hath reigned; States, Miniſters, People, give thankes to the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, which was, and is, and is to come, that he hath taken poore <hi>England,</hi> and the Kingdomes United, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meaſure from the hand of Antichriſt, and put his Name on them; O bow downe and worſhip, ſo the 24 Elders, the Church repreſentative, do at the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets ſound for the exaltation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But why are not the foure Beaſts,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> being the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Emblems, joyned here in theſe gratulations, as in other places? It a ſilence obſerved by ſome, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at,<note place="margin">Revel. 5.8. Revel. 19.4.</note> ſeeing before and afterward they are expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly named as leaders in the Churches triumphant Songs.</p>
            <p>It is conceived by ſome,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> that at this time of Chriſts firſt taking Kingdomes from the Beaſt, the Miniſtry for the generall ſhould be ſo bad and earthy, luke-warme and worldy, as that they had no heart to bleſſe the Lord for ſuch Reformation. And ſure it may note ſuch a time, and experience, in the Reformation thus farre manifeſts, that many to one have bin repining at it. Yet let nott his be caſt as a reproach to thoſe few that are found faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, (as too much it is, and under the name of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull Miniſtry, the faithfulleſt are deſpiſed) for the true labouring Miniſtry of Chriſt, are found leading the Church againe in their laſt Triumphant Songs over An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts ruines.<note place="margin">Revel. 19.4.</note> Let us be humbled for former failings, and renew the firſt love, and labour mightily for our Lord and his Chriſt, let him alone then to plead the cauſe of his faithfull servants, he will make their name ſhine forth as the Sunne in brightneſſe out of the darkeſt cloud.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Give up your ſelves &amp; kingdom (Honord Senators) more and more to the name, Law, and Government of our Lord and his Chriſt. As the Lord takes not all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114171:23"/>up at once, So neither any Kingdom to the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of <hi>Reformation</hi> at one time, becauſe he hath ſet them here in a growing State; there were no roome for growth in perfection. Experience hath taught us this will of God; O let us work with God more to be his, by giving up our names to him, by owning his Law, and honouring his Government by obedience.<note place="margin">Pſal. 2, 12.</note> This is to kiſſe the Sonne eminently and abundantly, and we ſhall not be deſpiſed for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yee <hi>VVorthies of this State</hi> in whom Chriſt reigns, act from him and to him, feed his people in the Land in his Paſtures, hold out unto them his Lawes, judge e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually and impartially in his matters; juſtifie the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, condemne the wicked, maintain ſaving Truths, and damne thoſe lyes that lead unto deſtruction. Shew your ſelves to bee <hi>deputed Gods</hi> indeed: Be, as hee is, ſimple, impaſſible, independent upon creatures; and act as he acts, freely, powerfully, wiſely, impartially, and conſtantly in the way of righteouſneſſe, ſo ſhall ye be truely the Sonnes of the moſt High, and the Lord ſhall be ſeen gloriouſly to reigne in you. The righteous and holy people will be obedient to you, and bleſſe God for you: and the mouth of wickedneſſe ſhall bee ſtopt for ever. Theſe incouragements may quicken and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then your hands. And then an end.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord is gone out before you, and hath begun to owne <hi>England,</hi> matching it out of the Dragons Paw, and Antichriſts power, and for 89 yeares hath been our Law-giver. Obſerve his preſence and workings and be ſtrengthned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The time is now for bringing in more Kingdomes from Satan to God, from Antichriſt to Chriſt; what elſe make all the ſhakings in all the Kingdomes of the world at this time. Study this time of God, and worke with Providence, now you have a ſeaſon to helpe up Gods holy mountaine, where no hurting nor deſtruction ſhall be.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:114171:24"/>
            <p n="3">3. This worke of the Lord and his Chriſt ſhall not go backward any more in the whole. The great Apoſtaſie is paſt, and now Kingdomes muſt be given to God, and Reformation by degrees ſhall be finiſhed, oppoſitions of wicked ſhall bee but ſtrong gales of winde to drive it home the ſooner: Gods Word is ſure, <hi>Babel</hi> ſhall fall and never riſe, and <hi>Zion</hi> ſhall be raiſed and never fall.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Lord Chriſt ſhall reigne for eve and ever, He hath overcome and ſat down in his Fathers Throne; He ſhall now trample upon his enemies, and make them his Foot-ſtoole, but he ſhall put the Crowne upon the heads of his Saints. Let you hearts then be comforted and your hands ſtrengthned, ye men of God, to the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation-work</hi> at this day; Make <hi>England</hi> more the Lords then ever, by the power he hath given you: ſo ye, and the people of this Land by experience will make the Churches confeſſion good,<note place="margin">Iſai. 26. 13.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord our God, other Lords beſides thee have had dominion over us, but by thee onely will we make mention of they Name.</hi> Your cry will bee, Lord reigne thou over us, no King but Chriſt for us, no People but the Saints. Now the Lord of all Lords, the King eternall through his Chriſt give you the ſpirit of Wiſdome, Truth, Unity, and Zeale to work mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for our God, and finiſh his Will in theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, that unto him in all the Churches of the Saints may be given praiſe and glory everlaſting. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114171:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
